Did you know that you were doing algebra
way back in the second grade, way back
in elementary and primary school? Now, a
lot of you are saying, "Hey, Mr. YouTube
Math Man, I wasn't doing this in my
school." Well, indeed you were, but the
problem looked a little bit different.
So, what am I talking about? Well, what
we have here is an algebraic equation.
So, we have 2x + 1 is equal to 5. Now, x
is a variable. It simply just represents
a number. So a variable in algebra is
just some number. So we can think of
this equation this way. 2 * some number
x + 1 is equal to 5. Now way back in
elementary and primary school, we didn't
see algebraic equations written this
way. We saw them written in this manner.
So maybe something like this. Two box +
1 is equal to five. Now, of course, we
all remember these problems and then we
would just kind of look at this box and
think to ourselves, all right, what
number do I have to put into this box to
solve this problem? So, maybe you put in
a one, you're like, well, 2 * 1, that's
two. So, 2 + 1, that's three. Uh, one is
not the right answer. So, now maybe you
put in a two. And you get 2 * 2, that's
four. So, 4 + 1 is equal to five. So,
two is the right answer. And then of
course your teacher would give you a
nice little happy face and a bunch of
stars. So yes indeed this right here is
algebra. So instead of an x to represent
a number what we have here is another
symbol a box. All right. So 2 * a box +
1 is equal to 5. But this is an
algebraic equation. All right. All
right, so let's talk about how to solve
this equation uh using algebra and not
just kind of a guess and check method
because we could do the same thing here.
We can simply plug in some numbers for x
until we get the right answer. But in
algebra, what we want to do is figure
out what x is equal to. So the way we're
going to do that is get all of our uh
variables on the left hand side. So in
this case, it would just be x and then
one number on the right hand side. So to
do that we have to follow the golden
rule of algebra and that is whatever we
do to one side of the equation we have
to do the exact same thing on the other
side. All right. So the first thing that
we're going to do is subtract one from
both sides of the equation. Then add
down in a column manner. All right. So
we're going to get 2x + nothing is 2x. 1
- 1 is zero. And this is going to be
equal to 5 - 1 which is 4. Okay. So to
solve for x, all we have to do is divide
both sides of the equation by two. So x
is equal to 2, which is the right
answer. For more math help, make sure to
check out the link in the description
and the comment section.